<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glasse for Christians; or, The comfortable doctrine of adoption Wherein euery true beleeuer may behold his blessed estate in the kingdome of grace. By Thomas Granger, preacher of Gods Word at Butterwike in Holland in Lincolnshire.</title>
            <author>Granger, Thomas, b. 1578.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855597</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855597</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21097</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21097)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1519:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glasse for Christians; or, The comfortable doctrine of adoption Wherein euery true beleeuer may behold his blessed estate in the kingdome of grace. By Thomas Granger, preacher of Gods Word at Butterwike in Holland in Lincolnshire.</title>
                  <author>Granger, Thomas, b. 1578.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf contain a woodcut in a border of type ornaments.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; as filmed lacks the first and last leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Adoption (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21097:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21097:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LOOKING-GLASSE FOR CHRISTIANS; <hi>OR, THE COMFORTABLE</hi> Doctrine of Adoption.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN EVERY TRVE BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer may behold his bleſſed Eſtate <hi>in the kingdome of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS GRANGER, Preacher of Gods Word, at <hi>Butterwike</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> William Lones.</p>
            <p>1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21097:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21097:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND Vertuous Lady, the Lady HARRINGTON; Grace and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, and worthy Lady: As God hath made you three and foure times happy in your inward ſelfe, ſo hath he made you thrice happy alſo in your outward ſelfe, as in your State, in your bleſſed Iſſue, in your Name; which as the ſweete odour of a pretious oyntment, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth thoſe that are neere by, and a far off, euen the children of God, who receiue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſtrength by the graces of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the more principall members, whoſe pleaſant influence giueth vigour and more liuely motion to the inferiour and weaker. This happines the Lord ſtill continue, that as both you and all the children of God haue receiued grace for grace, &amp; glory for glory; ſo you may with them be perfected in glory at that ioyfull and long expected day of our Lords appearing, and full redemption of the
<pb facs="tcp:21097:3"/>
purchaſed poſſeſſion. In the meane ſpace, I being a ſtranger vnto you, yet a Miniſter of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, doe greatly reioyce to heare that you, and other perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of State and Birth, doe walke vprightly in the Truth. And as your Faith, Zeale, and Deuotion, moſt worthy fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are a comfort to me &amp; others: ſo for your comfort alſo, I ſend to you <hi>A Diuine Loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glaſſe,</hi> wherein, I hope well, you ſhall behold your bleſſed ſtate, euen the beauty and glory of your perſon in the ſight of God, and in the ſight of your owne ſoule. To the poore (in ſpirit) is the rich Goſpell offered; from the poore (my ſelfe) is this rich treaſure ſent vnto you: in it ſelfe rich, but a poore mite as handled and deliuered from mee, yet ſuch ſhall it be, as your Honor ſhall pleaſe to accept.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all<lb/>
Chriſtian duty to be<lb/>
commanded;<lb/>
THOMAS GRANGER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:21097:3"/>
            <head>A LOOKING GLASSE for Chriſtians.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Epheſ. 1. 5.</bibl>
                  <p>Who hath predeſtinated vs to the adoption of ſonnes by Ieſus Chriſt vnto himſelfe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good pleaſure of his will.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Third verſe aforego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Apoſtle propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the generall doctrine of all the ſpirituall bleſſings of God the Father towards vs in his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, the matter, foundation, and meritorious cauſe therof.</p>
            <p>From the 4. verſe to the end of the 14. verſe, he declareth, that generall Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by an induction, or recitall of the ſpecials applied to his purpoſe here aym'd at, which is to reduce them to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſincerity of faith, and obedience. In the 4. ver. he maketh mention of Electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſanctification. In this 5. verſe, of Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In the 6. verſe, of Iuſtification. In the 7. verſe, of Redemption. In the 8. 9. 10. verſes, of the Goſpell with the effects, and
<pb facs="tcp:21097:4"/>
power thereof. In the 11. verſe, of glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. In the 12. 13. verſes, of Faith. In the 14. ver. of the teſtimony of the Spirit, the pledge of our aſſurance, in ſealing the ſame in, and to our ſpirits.</p>
            <p>In this 5. verſe he mentioneth the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bleſſing of <hi>Adoption,</hi> which he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth by ſundry arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1 By the principall efficient cauſe. <hi>[who hath predeſtinated vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 He layeth downe the bleſſing it ſelfe. <hi>[To the adoption of ſonnes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in poſitionem filiorum.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 By the meanes <hi>[by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4 By the end.</hi> [to himſelfe, or into him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5 By the impulſiue cauſe</hi> [according to the good pleaſure of his will <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>)</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1 Concerning the firſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is the moſt high, and hidden cauſe of all things, both of their ends, and of their meanes, Decreed in the wiſdome of God from Eternity, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his preſcience, and ordered by his prouidence. In the generall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is called Deſtination, in the more ſpecial, <hi>i.</hi> reſtrained to man, Predeſtinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:4"/>
Predeſtination hath two parts, Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Reprobation.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>Of Election there is a twofold end</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Principall.</item>
                        <item>Inferiour.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall end reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth the</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Glory of God. verſ. 6.</item>
                        <item>Glorification of Man, verſe 11.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The inferiour ends are the meanes of ſaluation, and of Gods glory in ſauing vs. They are diuers, and ſubordinate one to another. The firſt is effectuall voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, verſ. 8. 9. 10. The ſecond is Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, verſ. 6. 7. The third is Faith, verſ. 12. 13. The fourth is Adoption, verſe. 5. The fifth is Sanctification, verſ. 4. The ſixth is the Obſignation of all theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in our hearts by the ſpirit, verſ. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2. Concerning Adoption it ſelfe.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>A ſonne of God may be ſo called by</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Nature.</item>
                        <item>Grace.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. By Nature Ieſus Chriſt is the onely Sonne of God, begotten of the Father by an incomprehenſible and ineffable gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſonnes of God by Grace, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king grace in the largeſt ſence, are ſo
<list>
                     <item>
                        <label>by</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>Creation.</item>
                           <item>Adoption.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:5"/>
1. By Creation, the Angels, <hi>Iob</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. and <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 38.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Adoption, <hi>Adam</hi> after his fal, &amp; all elected in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> (who are ſpecially called children by Adoption &amp; Grace, beeing reſtrained by Diuines to the grace of redemption) in whom alone wee recouer the nature &amp; name of Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And we are called ſonnes by Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe when wee were by nature the children of wrath, wee haue receiued the right and title of ſonnes from God, by and for Chriſt, and in him the ſonnes of God, &amp; conſequently with him heyres both of this world, and of that which is to come.</p>
               <p>This affection and action of God is expreſſed by a terme borrowed from the ciuill Law: For Adoption (as it is in the Inſtitutions) is an act of Law imitating Nature, ordeyned for their comfort which haue no children. If the adopted was a free man, <hi>viz.</hi> neyther vnder the authority of a father, nor of a maiſter, it was termed adrogation, but if hee was vnder the power and command of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it was called ſimple adoption.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:5"/>
In olde times adoption was in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vſe, both among Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. In <hi>Gen.</hi> 48. 5. <hi>Iacob</hi> adopted <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> and named his owne name vpon them. So 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. 8. <hi>Michol</hi> the daughter of <hi>Saul,</hi> and wife of <hi>Dauid,</hi> is ſaid to beare fiue children to <hi>Adriel</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Barzillai;</hi> But God puniſhed <hi>Michol</hi> with barrenneſſe, becauſe ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided the zeale of <hi>Dauid</hi> dancing before the Arke. So <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſaid to bee the ſonne of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter. Moreouer, children were adopted to the dead, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25. 5. For if a man died without children, his brother was, by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to marry his wife, to raiſe vp ſeede to his brother, and the firſt-borne ſonne was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med after his father deceaſed.</p>
               <p>For the further cleering of this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, Adoption is conſummate, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choate. The former is perfect, and it is the ſtate of the Elect in the kingdome of glory. The latter is imperfect, and of it there are two degrees, according to the nonage or full age of the Church. The nonage was the ſtate of it before Chriſt, when it was vnder Tutors and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors,
<pb facs="tcp:21097:6"/>
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 1. 2. trayned vp in Chriſt, &amp; vnto Chriſt, by the rigour of the Morall Law, and lenity of the Ceremoniall Law, this drawing, the other driuing. And of that nonage there we e degrees alſo; for there were ſome more Ceremonial, others Euangelicall men, as <hi>Dauid, Salomon, Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> the Prophets, &amp;c. yet all inferiour to <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who heard and ſaw, what they a farre off perceiued. So that hauing a leſſe meaſure of the Spirit, the Law had more force ouer them, as the rod and repreſentations haue ouer chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in whom reaſon is weake. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was called the ſpirit of bondage, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15.</p>
               <p>The fulneſſe of time, or age of the Church, is after Chriſt, which hath two degrees alſo, youth &amp; perfect age: youth is the weakeneſſe of the children of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1. which in the truely regenerate groweth more and more to ſtrength and perfection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 16, and 4 13. The perfect age or ſtrength, is the <hi>plerophory</hi> or ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Faith, Hope, Loue, euen of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, poſſeſſion, aſſurance. And it is
<pb facs="tcp:21097:6"/>
the Chriſtian mans happineſſe in this world, as the pleaſant Land was to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his poſterity before actuall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion: yea this ſpirituall is greater then that earthly, in that he is already come in the fleſh, and aſcended to prepare a place for vs in whom all the promiſes of God are <hi>Yea and Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perfect men are more ſpecially termed ſpirituall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1. the other carnall, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3 of the vigour of the olde man, and weakeneſſe of the new. Through the greater reuelation of Gods wiſdome and loue to vs in Chriſt ſince his aſcenſion &amp; aſſurance of his loue to vs, the Holie Ghoſt is called in ſpeciall manner, the ſpirit of adoption, teaching, teſtifying, in ſealing the ſame more aboundantly to vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15. But how? not that we are voyd of all feare; for as Gods loue is more aboundantly reuealed, ſo are his iudgements alſo; as grace <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, ſo is ſinne alſo: and as Chriſt hath ſet open the gates of heauen, euen more aboundantly reuealed the celeſtiall glory that could be done by the figures of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the materiall Temple;
<pb facs="tcp:21097:7"/>
ſo hath he more fully manifeſted the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe torments of the wicked, that deſpiſe grace offered, which breedeth greater ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the Conſcience, then the legall threatnings of temporall puniſhments. A child offending feareth the rod, but a man feareth Impriſonment and Death. Hence it is that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Feare hath pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, but perfect loue caſteth out feare.</hi> He that loueth, reioyceth euermore. Hee that beleeueth, yet wanteth feeling, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth on Chriſt by faith, and is Chriſts as well as the other, though he know not ſo ſenſibly that he is Chriſts as the other doth. The perfect man knoweth himſelfe to be heyre of the kingdome of glory, as the louing and dutifull ſonne is aſſured of his fathers inheritance. The other alſo may know that hee is Chriſts, if hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on none other, nor other meanes, and Chriſt forſaketh none, that doe not firſt forſake him; which forſaking ſtands rather in affection than action. For <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>That to will was preſent with him,</hi> though he did that which was euill (vnwillingly). And he had comfort and reioycing, becauſe hee did not euill euilly.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:7"/>
To explane this a little farther, There are fiue kindes of feare.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Diabolicall, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Naturall. It is an affection or paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heart, whereby we feare not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly death or diſſolution, but alſo dangers and euils, that are deſtructiue of our good eſtate and wel-fare. This feare is by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral inſtinct in all ſenſible creatures, as well as in man, and in the godly as men, yea in Chriſt, as he was man, and ſubiect to our infirmities. This feare of it ſelfe is not ſinne, but the corruption, <hi>(ataxie &amp; anomie)</hi> thereof is ſinne, as when we doe not order it according to the law of God. But Chriſt in fearing death, did alſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe to the Decree and Will of his Father, according to the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord: by God with all thine heart,</hi> &amp;c. So feare was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of loue, or rightly ordered by loue. So the godly feare death, yet humble themſelues to death and all croſſes, for the loue of God extenuateth and caſteth out feare.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Worldly feare. This is the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of naturall feare, when as men deny
<pb facs="tcp:21097:8"/>
Chriſt in what meaſure ſoeuer, that they might not looſe their goods, worldly eſteeme, pleaſures, preferments, &amp;c. Worldly-minded men are full of this fear, and their feare ſhall fall on them, <hi>Math.</hi> 10. 28. and if our hearts condemne vs, then is God greater then our hearts, much more to condemne vs. Examples of ſuch feares, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 12. 42. and 11. 48. Howbeit Gods children are of infirmity affected with it ſometimes, as <hi>Nicodemus, Ioh.</hi> 3. 2 And the Diſciples, eſpecially <hi>Peter.</hi> But if we ſinne and feare, wee haue an aduocate with the Father, Ieſus Chriſt the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp;c. As for the feare of the wicked, it is without all loue, and comfort of hope.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Servile feare, (which is voyd of loue, and hope.) It is proper to the wicked. It proceedeth of an euill conſcience. <hi>Prou.</hi> 28. 1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 20. 21. It hath two effects. 1. It reſtrayneth the furious, and curbeth the violent. <hi>Act.</hi> 24. 25. 2 It works hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart through deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſome, when it groweth to an height of wicked reſolution, all hope through Satan being vtterly quenched.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:8"/>
5 Filliall, or ſonelike feare. It is proper to the regenerate, who by this feare are mooued to a voyd ſinne, and to liue god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily. It ariſeth from the knowledge of God, and our ſelues, and from the feeling of his accep ation and loue of vs, wrought in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt. Hereof <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prou.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. 10. <hi>Iob.</hi> 28. 28.</p>
               <p>More plainely, this feare is thus begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Firſt, when a man heareth the lawe, what is there commaunded, what forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, the Holy Ghoſt commeth and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the vaile of naturall blindnes, and ſlumbring, cauſing him to ſee his ſin, and to feele the wrath of God vpon him, euen to lay them both to his hard heart, wherevpon feare troubleth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, and breaketh the hard heart.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when a man in this caſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Goſpell, the Holy Ghoſt inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the minde to vnderſtand &amp; beleeue, and to apply the promiſes to himſelfe, whereupon he begines to feele quyetnes, and peace of conſcience, being more and more perſwaded that he is beloued of God. Now on this perſwation ariſeth the
<pb facs="tcp:21097:9"/>
loue of God for his loue, mercy, and grace in Chriſt. On this loue ariſeth a new feare namely, to diſpleaſe God, ſo louing and mercifull to vs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 4.</p>
               <p>Of this filiall feare there are foure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, expreſſed &amp; illuſtrated by the feare of children towards their Parents, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there are foure degrees. Firſt, a childe loueth his parents, and flies to them as his chiefe refuge, yet is he held in obedience with threatning, and feare of the rodde, this may in ſpeciall be called ſeruile, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 1. Secondly, partly by reaſon, partly by the rod. Thirdly, leſſe by the rod, and more by reaſon. Fourthly, by reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone without the rod. This is perfection in this ſtate of imperfection. The appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and amplification hereof I leaue to the Chriſtian Reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3. Concerning the meanes of Adoption.</head>
               <p>Hee that adopteth a ſeruant or bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, giueth a price for his redemption or ranſome, euen ſo hath God redeemed vs with a price, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4. Concerning the end of Adoption.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:9"/>
It is that we might be his, not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor yet our owne. The ſeruant or bondman adopted, liueth no longer to his former Maſters, but to his Adopter, not in ſeruitude, but in freedome, not in ſlauiſh, but in ſon-like feare, <hi>viz.</hi> awfull reuerence and loue. Euen ſo we being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted, liue no longer to our former ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and tyrants to whom we were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled, and willingly did homage, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the darkeneſſe of our mindes, and deadneſs of our benummed Conſciences, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 17. 18. namely, to the world, the fleſh, and the Diuell. Euery naturall man is a bondſlaue to theſe tyrants, and ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of his miſery. The beſt Heathen, the beſt Iew are not better, how glorious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be. Among the Heathen <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtides</hi> was the moſt iuſt, <hi>Socrates</hi> the moſt vertuous, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the moſt learned, <hi>Plato</hi> the moſt diuine, <hi>Lucretia</hi> the moſt chaſt, <hi>Aeneas</hi> the moſt pious. Among the Iewes, the <hi>Eſſees</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> were moſt deuout, and among them <hi>Paul</hi> the moſt feruent in zeale, vnblameable, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. the patterne of perfection, as erroneouſly he iudged of himſelfe, being blinded by
<pb facs="tcp:21097:10"/>
the god of this world. But afterward he ſaw that his feruency was but fury. All theſe I ſay, euen the beſt Gentiles and Iewes admired for their vertues, beeing without Chriſt, were the children of wrath, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 1. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5. Concerning the impulſiue cauſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is the alone mercy and loue of God, 2.</hi> Tim. <hi>1. 9.</hi> Who hath ſaued vs, and called vs according to his purpoſe, and grace, &amp;c. Epheſ. <hi>2. 4. 5.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the more full vnderſtanding of this doctrine for our further edification and comfort, two things are to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. Firſt, the compariſon betweene ciuill and ſpirituall adoption. Secondly, the priuiledges, whereof we are made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers thereby.</p>
               <p>The compariſon is of their likeneſſe and vnlikeneſſe. Firſt, concerning their likeneſſe. Theſe two adoptions reſemble one another in eight particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The Adopter for the moſt part wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth children of his owne So God had no ſonnes, but his onely Sonne, Ieſus Chriſt, whom he gaue to redeeme vs out of the captiuity of ſinne and Satan, into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="tcp:21097:10"/>
liberty and priuiledge of ſonnes.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The Adopter out of his owne bountifulneſſe and kindneſſe chooſeth a ſonne where he pleaſeth, beeing obliged to none: Euen ſo God hath freely out of his owne loue and good pleaſure choſen vs. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>When the bountifulneſſe &amp; loue of God toward man appeared, &amp;c. Deut.</hi> 7. 7. 8. God loued not nor chuſed Iſraell becauſe they were more in number (which was in thoſe times a ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue and bleſſing) but becauſe hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them of his owne free mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The Adopter giueth a price for the redemption and liberty of the Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: ſo hath God giuen a price for vs, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. The party adopted is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſeruant or bondman: ſo were wee by nature the children of wrath, of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, of this world, of darkeneſſe, of the night, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">V. The Adopter offereth himſelfe as a Father, not as a ſeuere Maſter or Tyrant to his adopted ſonnes: euen ſo God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth himſelfe, and that in theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars principally.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:11"/>
1. In prouiding &amp; caring for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. 3. <hi>to</hi> 14. <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 30. 31. 32. Therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Caſt your care on God, for he eareth for you, Gen.</hi> 31. 4 God had care ouer <hi>Iacob</hi> againſt churliſh <hi>Laban,</hi> chap. 32. 9. 10. God prouided for <hi>Iacob</hi> alway; and God doth as much for all his children, but what God doth for vs, our childiſhneſſe conceiueth not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In chaſtiſements and corrections, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 7. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In trialls and temptations to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them, to proue them, to teach them, that he might doe them good at their lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8. 2. 3. 4. 5.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In patience, forbearance, long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 8. 9. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In hearing and granting their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 7. Now God granteth our prayers, when wee pray to him rightly. Of right prayer there be three degrees.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To pray to God the Father onely. This excludeth Atheiſme and heatheniſh Idolatry,</p>
               <p n="2">2. To pray to God through Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. This excludeth Turciſme, Iudaiſme, Popiſh idolatry.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:11"/>
3. To pray to the Father through the Sonne from an heart informed and moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the ſpirit of God. This excludeth all hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>The ſignes of an heart informed and mooued by the ſpirit of God, are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To pray according to the will of God, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To pray with an humble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 7. This is a ſpeciall ſigne; for pride is the roote and top of all ſinne. It was and is the ſinne of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and our firſt parents, who deſired to ſhake off the yoke of obedience, and to be equall with God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 5. 6. The pride of the Diuell was the glorifying of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with theſe excellencies wherewith the Lord had indowed him, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 6. Pride is directly oppoſite to God and his glory: it is the maine ſinne, others are the by. Couetouſneſſe is the roote of all euill, but as the purueyor of pride; euery co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous man is proud, and there is none of thoſe ſinnes, as pride of apparell, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, prodigality, feaſtings, &amp;c. which the couetous ſeemeth to hate, but hee would commit them if they were as gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:21097:12"/>
as niggardſhip, and drudgery is; for what will not the couetous doe for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney?</p>
               <p n="3">3. To pray in Faith, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To pray with feruency, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. 16.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To pray for ſpirituall graces eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and ſimply, and for other things as ſub-ſeruant thereto, <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 33.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To ayme at Gods glory one'y, as the three firſt petitions of the Lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er teach vs. He that prayeth thus, ſhall neuer bee denied any thing, neyther in kinde meaſure, nor manner. Thus Chriſt prayed, and was heard in all things: and thus doe all the children of God in ſome meaſure pray. If they obtaine not, it is becauſe of their weakeneſſe, wherein ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſtandeth. Howſoeuer, God accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the obedience, and with-holdeth no good thing; yea, hee giueth that which themſelues would onely aske, if in this life they were perfect, as Chriſt was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and as they ſhall be in the kingdom of glorý.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. The adopted doth offer himſelfe as a ſonne, not as a ſeruant. So doe the children of God in louing him in his
<pb facs="tcp:21097:12"/>
word and worſhip, in obeying him, in taking correction at his hands, in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelues to be taught and led by him. <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Deutronomy</hi> repeating all the benefits of God towards the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, at length concludeth. <hi>And now O Iſraell what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to loue the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Ioſua</hi> likewiſe, <hi>chap.</hi> 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14. repeating Gods benefits towards them in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, concludeth, <hi>Now therefore feare the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. By the Ciuill Law, the Heyre is reputed one and the ſame perſon with him that made him his heyre. In like ſort we are ſo neere conioyned with God by Chriſt, that we are made one and the ſame with him, as our Sauiour prayed, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17. 12. <hi>I pray thee O Father, that they all may be one, as thou art in mee, and I in thee, ſo they may be one in vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee are conjoyned, or vnited to Chriſt by two degrees.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We are vnited to the fleſh of Chriſt; for he is the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> therefore fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bones, as the Iews were wont to ſay of themſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:13"/>
which were deſcended of the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtocke, <hi>viz.</hi> of the ſame Father and Mother.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Wee participate of the ſpirit of Chriſt (not eſſentially, but effectually) who worketh in ſome meaſure the ſame properties and qualities in vs, which were in Chriſt, as he was man, which is called our transforming into Chriſt, and our putting on of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This coniunction <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth by ingraffing, wherein theſe two degrees of vnion doe euidently appeare; for the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and the ſtocke make one indiuiduall thing. For firſt, their matters are vnited into one, and cloſely cemented together, yet are they but <hi>contigua,</hi> neerely glued together. Therefore this Vnion is yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They participate of one iuyce, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and life, and are now <hi>continua,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, beeing contained vnder one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>forme.</hi> And this vnion is now inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable. Chriſt himſelfe expreſſeth this by a compariſon drawne from the vine and the branches, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. which haue one common life and ſpirit, by which
<pb facs="tcp:21097:13"/>
they grow burgeon, and fructifie, Yet heerein there is a difference; for the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence conuerteth the iuyce of the ſtocke into his owne nature and property: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, Chriſt conuerteth and transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs into his nature, that are incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into him.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth this vnion by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, wherein theſe two degrees are manifeſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt degree, is the outward bond or ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of wedlock, which conſiſteth of two parts or degrees. 1. A ſeparation of eyther from all others. 2. A mutuall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or enterchange.</p>
               <p>Second degree, is the inward bond, <hi>viz</hi> the coniugall affection, or mutuall loue and ſympathy. So the vnion of Chriſt with vs, is the vnion of our natures, and the vnion of his ſpirit with ours, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are made fleſh of his fleſh, &amp; bone of his bones ſpiritually as he is made fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bones cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally. Hence wee grow vp into him, and beare fruit in him; yet theſe vertues of the ſpirit in Chriſt are pure and perfect, and without meaſure, but in vs they are
<pb facs="tcp:21097:14"/>
meaſurable, and obſcured with ſundry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, both of our corrupt nature, and perſonall frailties; euen as the light of the Sunne is the ſame, but diuerſified in ſundry ſtarres, and glaſſes of diuers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. The Inheritance is confirmed and finally appropriated to the heyre by the death of the teſtator; ſo is our inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance by the death of Chriſt. This of the likeneſſe of theſe two adoptions.</p>
               <p>Now concerning their vnlikeneſſe. It ſtands in foure particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Adopter is mooued vvith the conſideration of ſome dignity and deſert in the adopted. Contrarily, God found no motiue of loue at all in vs. For vvee were his enemies. And our loathſomnes in his ſight, is ſet forth vnder a double allegorie, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16. where vnder the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of a forlorne infant is ſet downe the ſtate of the Iſraelites in Egypt, and our eſtates by nature in the ſtate of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites in the bondage of <hi>Pharao,</hi> a type of the Deuill.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Adopter giueth gold, or ſome other earthly thing for a ranſome, but
<pb facs="tcp:21097:14"/>
God hath giuen his onely ſonne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Adopter cannot giue the ſpirit of a naturall ſonne to the adopted: but God hath giuen vnto vs the ſpirit of ſonnes, by whom we call him <hi>(abba)</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen as naturall ſonnes doe their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The Adopted ſonne may loue his Adopter onely outwardly, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that he hath receiued, and reward that he expecteth, yet in heart he may be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienated, as to wiſh the death of his Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he may inherit his houſe &amp; land, as the Poet ſpeaketh of ſome vnnaturall ſonnes.
<q>
                     <l>Filius ante diem patrios inquirit in annos.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But contrarily, the children of God, are vnited vnto him in the inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heart, though outwardly they faile in many things, yea hyppocrits are oft times out-wardly more officious than they, as deceitfull ſeruants are often more obſequious than children. Therefore ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi> Pſal. 32. 2. <hi>Bleſſed is he, in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</hi> Not with ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his manifold infirmities.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21097:15"/>
The Second thing is the Priviledges, whereof we are made partakers by vertue of adoption.</p>
               <p>I By vertue of Adoption, we are made the brethren of Chriſt. In this reſpect he is called our elder brother. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 29. and <hi>Math.</hi> 28. 10. and 25. 40.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiect.</hi> Than before the Nativitie, death and Reſurrection of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> none were the adopted ſonnes of God, ſeeing that by the death and merits of Chriſt, wee are reconciled to God, called, iuſtified, adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Miſerable therefore was the ſtate of all before the incarnation of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The birth, and ſonſhip of Chriſt, tooke the begining from the everlaſting Counſell and Decree of God, wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his blood is ſaid to be ſhed from the begining of the world. <hi>Adam</hi> was iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and adopted by faith in Chriſt to come, whom God Preached, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Paradiſe, and was figured by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of the Law, which was interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Prophets, and fulfilled by Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>To be the brother of Chriſt is a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous title &amp; priuiledge. In an earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:21097:15"/>
we thinke it a great prerogatiue to be the kinſman of a Prince, and a ſpeciall priuiledge to be the Kings ſonne. In the ſpirituall kingdome &amp; Church of Chriſt, euery true beleeuer hath his prerogatiue and priuiledge. And if men deſire to match with perſons of birth &amp; bloud, for the aduancement of their names and houſes; much more ſhould we deſire this bleſſing of Adoption, for the euerlaſting aduancement of our names and ſtates.</p>
               <p>The bondman or Gally-ſlaue thinketh it a great happineſſe to be freed, &amp; made the adopted ſonne of a Prince, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Kings ſonne. This priuiledge haue wee receiued, let vs take notice of our happineſſe, and caſt off our ſlauiſh conditions.</p>
               <p n="2">II. By vertue of Adoption wee are made heyres of the heauenly Kingdome, euen coheyres with Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17. And if it bee ſo great a priuiledge to bee heyre apparent to an earthly kingdome, much more greater glory is it to haue right to, and in the kingdome of glory.</p>
               <p n="3">III. By vertue of Adoption wee are made Kings, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. 6. of greater might
<pb facs="tcp:21097:16"/>
and power than <hi>Nabuchadnezzar,</hi> that ſent out <hi>Holofernes,</hi> (as the Apocryphar mentioneth) to cut down all, that would not ſubmit themſelues vnder his yoke: greater than <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> that boaſted ſo of his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 127. Prouinces: yea than <hi>Alexander</hi> would haue beene, if hee had obtained that plurality of worlds, whereof <hi>Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> informed him. Hee hath made vs Kings and Prieſts to God his Father. We are made Kings, not in reſpect of an earthly Kingdome, ſeeing that the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God are oft times the moſt baſe and contemptible of an other: but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a ſpirituall kingdome, to which God hath ginen vs title and intereſt, in, and by Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 32.</p>
               <p>The faithfull are made Kings in three reſpects. 1. Becauſe they are Lords and Conquerors of their enemies, Sinne, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, the World, Death, Hell. 2. They are partakers of the Kingdome of Chriſt, and of Saluation; for wee haue receiued of Chriſt grace for grace, and glory for glory. 3. They haue Intereſt, Dominion, and Soueraignty of all things by Chriſt. But Chriſt alone is vniuerſall King, and
<pb facs="tcp:21097:16"/>
abſolute Lord. But the faithfull are kings as they participate with Chriſt in his kingdom, &amp; by vertue of this priviledge they ſhalbe Iudges of men, and <hi>Angels. Math.</hi> 10. 28. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. 3. <hi>The Saints ſhall iudge the world,</hi> and evill Angels. But how? In that they ſhall be as it were Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſours, and Aſſiſtants with Chriſt on the bench giving in voyce, and conſent with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiection.</hi> The wicked are Lords, and owners of worldly things alſo, how then belongeth this Priviledge to the adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſonnes of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. Adam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> was the ſonne of God by creation, and heyre of all things, but by the fall he loſt for himſelfe, and his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the right, and name of heyre, and ſonne, ſo that both he, and we by nature are onely vſurpers. But Chriſt by his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction hath purged our ſinnes, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled vs to God, and recovered the right of ſonnes and inheritance. For he being the true owner and ſight heyre of all things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath made vs that are in him, ſonnes and heyres of all things with him, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>As he hath giuen
<pb facs="tcp:21097:17"/>
Chriſt ſo ſhall he much more giue vs all things with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The godly therefore are the true Lords, and owners of all things. Firſt, becauſe their perſons only are accepted. Secondly, Becauſe they vſe them rightly, that is, with a good conſcience, namely, to the glory of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 13. The promiſe was made to <hi>Abraham</hi> that he ſhould be the heyre of the world, not by the works of the Law, to wit, as he was a ſonne of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> but by the righteouſnes of faith, that is, as he was the ſonne of the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How then are the wicked poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors and owners?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Gods providence they haue poſſeſſion of the things of the world, but no right vnto them, I meane ſpirituall right. Therefore in the end of the world they ſhalbe rooted out, and burnt with fire, but the godly ſhall remaine for ever. <hi>Ahraham,</hi> and his poſterity had right to <hi>Canaan,</hi> foure hundreth yeares by the promiſe of God, before they had actuall poſſeſſion. <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. 14. The reaſon why they had not preſent poſſeſſion in it, is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb facs="tcp:21097:17"/>
                  <hi>The wickednes of the</hi> Amorites <hi>is not yet full.</hi> The vſurpers muſt poſſeſſe it foure hundreth yeares, and <hi>Abraham Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> are to haue but a part in the playne of <hi>Mamre</hi> in <hi>Hebron,</hi> purchaſed with their money of the vſurpers, and the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> were ſtrangers in <hi>Egypt,</hi> having no foot, nor poſſeſſion in the Earth in civill clame, or right, but by ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance, and will of their Lord <hi>Pharao.</hi> So <hi>Dauid</hi> had right to the kingdome of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> before preſent poſſeſſion, He muſt tarie for that till <hi>Saul</hi> be remooved out of the way, and in the meane ſpace ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecution, and affliction of the vſurper. In <hi>Math.</hi> 13. The <hi>tares</hi> muſt grow togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the wheate, and haue place in the Land with the wheate, by the permi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the houſholder, none can cutt them vp without the diſpleaſure of the Lord, not that the Lord loveth them, but becauſe he loveth the wheate, amongſt which they grow. So the wicked haue poſſeſſion of, but not right to the things of the world, ſaue onely in civill reſpect, and humaine Conſtitution. And the more rich, and great they are, the more hatefull
<pb facs="tcp:21097:18"/>
are they, and the greater condemnation waiteth for them.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII The Adopted ſonnes of God haue the <hi>Angels,</hi> as miniſtring ſpirits at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on them for their good <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>are they not all miniſtring ſpirits, ſent forth for their ſakes that all he heares of ſaluation?</hi> Pſal. 34. 11. <hi>The Angell of the Lord pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth round about them that feare him,</hi> &amp;c. 2. King. 6. 17. Math. 4. Alſo 1. King. 19. <hi>Elias</hi> flying from <hi>Iezabel</hi> is comforted, directed, and fed by an <hi>Angell.</hi> Alſo, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. The <hi>Angels</hi> bring <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> before the fierie deluge. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. <hi>Iacob</hi> fearing <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſaw Angells comming<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and he acknowledgeth that they were ſent to be his protectors, and conductours in his iourney, <hi>Gen,</hi> 24. 7. <hi>Abraham</hi> ſending his ſervant to take a wife for his ſonne <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac,</hi> is perſwaded that the Lord will ſend his <hi>Angell</hi> before him. Alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26 53. If Chriſts kingdome had been of this world, and that he had not ben appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God to ſuffer for man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſhould haue been reſcued by more than twelue Legious of Angels. And our Saviour faith, that children, and ſimple, ſilly, help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21097:18"/>
men haue <hi>Angells</hi> protecting, and ſaving them. For their <hi>Angell</hi> beholdeth the face of God, attending his pleaſure in their behalfe. Moreover, in the end of this world, the <hi>Angells</hi> carry the ſoules of the godly into the kingdome of glory, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. Laſtly, in the day of iudgement, they ſhall gather all the Elect together, as the houſe-holder gathereth wheat into his barne, but burneth the weedes and the chaffe, the prophane and hypocrites.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>V. All afflictions, troubles, and wants are turned into trialls and fatherly corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inflicted for their good,</hi> Rom. <hi>8. 28.</hi> All things worke together for good, to them that loue God, &amp;c. Pſal. <hi>89. 32.</hi> I will viſit their transgreſſions with the rod, &amp;c. but my louing kindneſſe will I not vtterly take from them.</p>
               <p>As the Iſraelites were prepared by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temptations and trialls in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for the land of <hi>Canaan, Deut.</hi> 8. and as <hi>Dauid</hi> was prepared by perſecutions, and afflictions for the kingdom of Iſrael, ſo are the children of God for the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Canaan;</hi> yea, they are chaſtned of the Lord by ſundry waies, and ſometimes
<pb facs="tcp:21097:19"/>
by bodily death, (as in the wilderneſſe) that they might not be condemned with the World, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. In the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes therefore of the children of God, there is matter of reioyſing and in the reioycing of the wicked, matter of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, feare and deſpaire.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:21097:19"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
